okay we begin
welcome everyone it is
the resumption of
our cohort
update the video description it's the
resumption of cohort one of the active
inference textbook group
it's our 14 okay could someone mute
Giuseppe or feel free to say whatever
you want to say
well uh can you hear me yes yes okay so
sorry but I'm completely new to this
interface of a gather and uh encoder so
I I'm not sure I understand cohort one
and cohort 2 here is that so because
cohort one was the wasn't it the
previous one like the the one that yes
the start last year
well it's still going on
from May till July
we did chapters one through five
okay now we are in this cohort so if
those who did not participate in this
part like respectfully you know thanks
for the question but everyone in general
respectfully let's try to have people
who are in the cohort participate in it
everyone's welcome to join and of course
re-watch but contributions in the
questions and the chat are probably best
so that we can respect the people who
are continuing on
this is our 14th meeting and now we're
heading into the second five chapters of
the book
okay does any other person want to give
oh yeah go ahead
hold on so the the the the current one
that is going on right now is the cohort
one and not cohort two we're all
learning in different stages so the
previous hour was the cohort that is
focusing on chapters one through five
okay stage they're in and now some of us
a different set of people some are
joining both so that's why we made the
meetings convenient was so that we could
like for many of us who want to do it
both we can join or there's but
this is a separate set of people
I see I see yes so okay so cohort true
was was first and then I mean right in
the this meeting in this meeting right
now cohort 2 was first yes and now
which started correct before we warmed
up the chapters one through five
okay so I
read it because I I subscribed for
cohort too so excellent okay good thank
you so much see you next time thanks for
setting up all this yeah this thing
okay bye bye yes awesome
okay
anyone else want to add anything
we don't need to do a coda overview
I would say people who are watching this
recording can look at the live recording
if they want a code to update that we
just went through
for the cohort twos live meetings
but does anyone
want to give any um
introductory thoughts otherwise there's
a few ways I think we can go for this
session
but we're here just to
rejoin our activities and Orient towards
chapters six or ten
we can scan through the chapters
we can have any suggestions or
discussions around
ways to approach them I don't know
uh Rohan and then anyone else
I was wondering when are we gonna get to
the projects part or discussions about
the projects
great question let's look at the
chapters and see where that first off it
can happen however you want
with contacting people and
um like we can make a sub page like I
see exists here this looks really
awesome
so people can request a sub page they
can mention it that contact them
now or however
so it's up to you for a project that is
under your control
it can be developed in the open here or
however
you can also participate in many ongoing
projects like active block fronts which
also
um which might all share this
are get coin Grant was approved
yesterday
so if people
are familiar with this or want to become
familiar this is a way to like provide
or receive support possibly
for their learning in blockburns and
contributing to that open source package
[Music]
um
does that address what you were thinking
were you thinking about these project
ideas or were you thinking more about
like the sort of build your own model
approach that will be starting in
chapter six
I know about uh project ideas in the
quota page
awesome yeah like these are
um
well they're they're different different
types of projects clearly more will be
added but they're of different
they're not necessary they might involve
building a generative model but they are
not
degenerative model itself or only
let's look at chapter six
because this is where the generative
model construction is going to come into
play and so again there's a lot of
projects that
you would only need to qualitatively
think about generative models for like
educational material production
is related to the generative model or
could be modeled as a generative model
of a learner
but you wouldn't necessarily have to
make a general model but in chapter six
um
it's a recipe for Designing active
inference models
it is going to rock sorry just real
quick uh I think Luke is here uh doesn't
have access against or access
okay okay
message in Discord or I mean messaging
gather your email address and I'll add
you
Okay so
sorry I didn't
oh okay you requested access all right
I'll add you that's enough then
um
in chapter six it's going to ask some
questions
that are uh driving the design of the
generative model
which system of remodeling
system of Interest
what is the appropriate form for the
generative model
reflecting the discrete or continuous
distinction that we looked at
and also all these other questions that
aren't exactly within the textbook like
temporal depth hierarchical nesting
which parameters are learned versus
fixed all these different directions
that the models actually have to be
elaborated on even before getting to the
data engineering and maybe even code
implementation
just from a structural perspective what
form is it
how to set up the generative model
is where some of those analytical
details begin being introduced
not necessarily even the program level
implementation or an executable
simulation but like
okay we have a preference Vector that's
is that is there two states are is there
some continuous preference distribution
whatever it is
what is the actual details of the
generative model
and then
the other side of the coin slash blanket
is the generative process
so what are the endogenous Dynamics
and the um causal mapping with action
for the generative process
and there's kind of cases where you have
more of a communication setting active
inference entities on both sides
you could also have more of like a
simple simple
partnering
like two um deterministic programs that
send messages to each other or it could
be like one more cognitive
more agent-like generative model and one
more
environmental non-living type
any thoughts or overviews or how would
people think about
how can we make this type of a recipe
design should we be all designing a
model or how do we even go about reading
a section of the book in a chapter that
begins with a
recipe provision Lyle
yeah so so I I spent a lot of time
building what I think would be classed
here as generative models and what I
find is that this what I I characterize
it as the step of framing it up framing
up is is often far trickier sometimes
much harder frankly than building a
model depending on what what the
situation is
and in my experience I find that it all
comes down to making sure we understand
what is the question that we're trying
to answer right it's sort of like
because because every modeling process
I'm sure everybody on this call knows is
the process of deciding what to leave
out right what to put in what to leave
out and what level of representation
then it all has everything that's in
there if it's going to be a good model
has to be
necessary and necessary to
answer a question or provide a
particular Insight or so forth so that
whole issue of framing out uh what
you're going to build you know and in
all those different the 10 000 questions
yeah there's more than four you know
ultimately it's many
then it's all about that which often
means understanding the audience if
if the model builder is the only
audience this is a much simpler if the
audience is
um
uh you know some much larger group with
different perspectives a lack of of
homogeneity and insight then there
almost has to be uh I'm gonna say almost
a pre-modeling or framing process
of of sort of of framing up what are the
questions we care about and then we can
talk about how how those translate into
a model
so
that's just some general framing
thank you that's very
interesting it it
um makes me think about like this
audience question for the model like why
are we building the model why are we
shaping our regime of attention to build
this model
building can be an end of itself it can
be creative and expressive and fun and
all these other things and maybe later
there's a road that has some pragmatic
value too but also it can just be like
fun like you know what would a
generative model that could do this look
like and that can be very didactic
there's other times where you're
presenting information
oh I made a simulation of Twitter
discourse and dot dot dot
is always going to be presented in a way
that's not only just like the model
distilling down from the world but then
you're communicating it and then when
you're actually not just communicating
but if you're making an application that
does something and communication is
doing something as well then
the system of Interest as Lyle mentioned
is totally non-trivial and there's the
whole framing
in some of these early stages especially
because they can't always be changed
easily later
um run and then anyone else
uh yeah uh so I'm just curious when you
say who's the audience uh
is it that uh like isn't this part of
the active inference model itself that
okay so whatever makes sense in that
framework wouldn't that be the audience
here
thank you
as in it has to survive right your agent
has to survive so whatever generic model
helps it survive
would that not be the
model of choice over here and I'm just
curious I'm not sure that's awesome it's
awesome like way to frame it and it's
it's um maybe someone can share the um
free energy governance link
in the in the chat I just can't look it
up right now but but um
it puts this very nicely in in a recent
pretty short book dissertation about
like that imperative for organizations
and um yes in one sense it can be said
the right generative model or like the
audience for it is whatever its
survivability conditions are but and
within our textbook group The
survivability conditions are open
however we're also learning about or
even just gesturing towards
like
okay
not just we're gonna imagine a room with
a person who can take on a jacket or
take it off
um we can make that a didactic model and
the audience could be this textbook
group
or future cohorts of the textbook group
and the function could be just sort of
like a
neutral
Exemplar
active inference generative model but
then of course the considerations for
information presentation empirical data
analysis any kind of application
the system of interest is not just the
one person with the jacket on or off two
states room with a sign fluctuation
so that's a different situation for
model building so is that how should we
interpret this recipe
oh okay okay
but is there not like a journal
framework for what a good generative
model looks like is what I'm saying like
I I guess you could frame that
definitely so if you want to build pixel
level representations for example you
can use again and that's a pretty decent
one but maybe pixel level
representations are not a good
uh not good for the task at hand or
something like that so it should be able
we should it should fit a general
category right so this is what a good
set of models looks like for active
inference so that that sort of is
getting it
yeah that's a very fascinating framing
does anyone want to add something to
that
is I I totally hear you like on what is
there a is there a rubric like what are
we evaluating the generative model
and process
fit
because it's not like there's just
simply a best generative model you know
bigger or you know whatever no future
about it
except outside of a generative process
um context is the fitness
and then what is their rubric is our
gold standard is it like oh you're
dealing with audio data here's the file
format
that level of standardization certainly
not
however are there some
um practices or lenses that we could
bring in from people's experience with
evaluating model adequacy and relevancy
there probably are
Lyle
well yeah that really comes right back
to purpose right so a model is always
fit for purpose
and and you of course this also surfaces
the questions of model validation right
one of the things we haven't talked
about here is what's the right model how
do we frame up the right model what do
we choose to put in what leave out part
of that is purpose and and how would I
evaluate you know if I do what I'm
imagining a model will be how do I
evaluate its quality its validity well
what data is actually available that's
one thing you always have to ask at the
outset what data is available what data
can I use what's computationally
you know adequate and what parts of this
then uh when we kind of project
you know when we apply this model if
that's its role then does it fit for the
purpose does it provide you know good
you know adequate results and improve to
be you know whatever Behavior we're
trying to address
so
you can't you can't say if it's good if
you don't have a purpose so if your
purpose is just to explore model
building which is something I love to do
then
that's a pretty big there's a lot of
things that are fit for that purpose
right but if the purpose is to
um uh you know Pro do a prospective uh
analysis of a system and what actions
might be taken to intervene then that's
in a different thing
thanks a lot for sharing it I'm I'm
really
happy and I think it's relevant that
we're having this kind of a discussion
because we've gone through some of the
first chapters
and we will continue through chapter six
I think into having this conversation
but
does anybody else want to add something
about this more General topic of like
how are we even coming to talk about
what system or how are we framing the
system that we're modeling
that's in section 6.3
I um
I mean this is too broad to it's not
active in French specific but
whenever I'm trying to model something
the only questions that I mean it is
contextual to the purpose it entails a
purpose in an audience but all I want to
know basically is
what are the questions that need this
model needs to like generate an answer
for
um what is the information that is like
necessarily therefore kind of required
to
Model A system that would have such
answers in it
uh
and maybe another
way to say the same thing is that
like what affordances
would the model acquire
to answer address
whatever the some set of questions that
are posed to the system so if you asked
you know
I don't know
um like how frequently does a yellow
colored car I don't know drive down this
particular Road
um then I wouldn't need to record like
the number of bikes or their colors
uh that are you know
using the bike lane or buses or trucks
large you know so and like this is um
maybe outside the scope of what I mean
by yellow how many
you know cars out of all the cars how
many are yellow or something that's
right driving down this road or whatever
um it's like
not a even exactly a generative model
but my point is that
modeling that system there there is
obvious data that's like completely
irrelevant right
um and so
uh
if you were going to build some sort of
simulation of any kind that's going to
be generative like
there's often a lot of data that's just
completely extraneous depending on what
questions you're going to ask of it
so
thanks
in six three
in the first paragraphs
they're gonna come out hard on the
interface concept of Markov blanket
this is how you'll do system modeling is
by finding interfaces that distinguish
the internal and external states of a
system
then
that
is critiqued or elaborated
because there's an infinite degrees of
freedom
in the core screenings and those are
modeler specific
and they suggest that that matters
especially if you want to be considering
embodied extended perspectives
where just descriptive
interfacing models won't give you the
whole answer there's a great paper could
a neuroscientist understand a
microprocessor
showing that even if you have total
access to the microprocessors firing
like an EEG and a generated set of
single and double lesions
a lot of the interpretations would be
strongly misleading
um yet people want the wiring Circuit of
the brain which is dynamic and also
involves diffusive molecules
we have all 302
nematode neurons mapped
but that also as an interface diagram is
not even close
so if you want to describe the nematode
like model building then it's a fit for
purpose
however there might be very simple
models
that could be doing a lot better in this
in
nematode Behavior observation
the form
is discussed there are three main design
choices first discrete and continuous
time we had some awesome discussions in
the previous months about like
similarities and differences
and where like in theory they're
different and then in practice where
they're different
the whole question of like discretizing
continuous systems
um the second choice is between shallow
models
and hierarchical models where inference
operates at multiple time scales
the third choice is the consideration
only of the present
kind of the variational free energy
versus models with temporal depth
temporal depth consideration could be
purely passive
and it could also include some elements
of
affordance
which if we remember to like the B
Matrix actions are influencing how
States the world are changing
through time so
that is how active inference is unifying
policy comparison by kind of embedding
action into
estimates of how things could evolve
probabilistically
those three design decisions are
explored in slightly more detail in the
subsections
six five how to set up the generative
model
after specification
then the specific variables have to be
included
okay the latent State temperature is
going to be continuous the observations
in my thermometer I'm going to take in
as just integers and then there's going
to be a person who is going to be in a
binary state of like whether it's hot or
cold or maybe I want hot neutral cold or
maybe I want them to have a 10 point
scale or I want them to have um a scale
that's doing Dot
that is in this stage of actually
setting up the generative model
and giving a little bit of like
color
to what had been
just outlined
it's going to be a nested model with
this continuous variable and this kind
of a discrete variable
um
here we return to the Frog
example from earlier in the book
where there's like but it's kind of
being generalized a little bit it was
introduced with the whole Bayesian
equation walkthrough now we're returning
to it and thinking more about multimodal
or like even you could consider this as
Sensor Fusion
because there's some hidden cause
the jumping or the action of a frog
that is inducing several domains of
impact potentially in the generative
process
and then that leads to specific
observables from the perspective of the
cognitive entity
those could be again two communicative
cognitive entities or one and not or
however
so this is like okay
we're going to be modeling
forest fires
so forest fires they change the
temperature they change the
chemical composition they change the
vibrations in the ground or something
okay and then maybe there's three
sensors maybe you have three
thermometers
and then what about them are you gonna
average them are they going to be like
three parallel modeled Time series
that is where some more specification of
the generative model comes into play
keeping
this the active inference ontology in
mind
what are the affordances the Frog what
are the latent States
that are being changing through time
like sound
physical presence or Photon emission or
something and then what are the data
that would be oh the observations
[Music]
um
this box looks like it's about
different sensory modalities I'm sure
there's a lot of interesting
discussions we could bring in here
priors and empirical Behavior
complete class theorems
any statistical decision procedure
Behavior may be framed as Bayes optimal
under the right set of Prior beliefs
discussion of fixed and learned
variables
one can imagine the pros and the cons
generally of having fixed and learned
variables
like
computationally it's simpler to fix a
hard-coded variable however if there's a
setting where the model's adequacy
depends on being able to update that
maybe you want it learnable
however then you have to deal with these
questions about like the kinetics of
learning like instantly switch or slow
switch or Trend averaging so there's a
lot of discussions around learning how
is attention
regulated what is precision on learning
it's like it very much complexifies the
model
and there's many variables that you can
bring into a learnable setting
but when it's framed as just static
variables
and only like the hidden States changing
through time that's like the simplest
case
but more and more cognitive entities
probably are going to entail
considering learning Dynamics
setting up the generative process
the reason we postponed the design of
the generative process
so
a little slate of hands
entity first not the um
Niche first is that in many practical
applications discussed in this book we
simply assume the Dynamics of the
generative process are the same or very
similar to the generative model
we generally assume the agent's
generative model closely mimics the
process that generates its observation
that is clearly a simplifying case
because it doesn't address
what if
you're paying attention to predicting
with and the world is dependent on
height
there's so many
complexities of that which is really
that broader like what is being modeled
what matters question
but in some
way very upstream or very close to the
Stream
it is like the rabbit being put in the
Hat
like if the rat knows that there's a 5x5
maze
that's a huge amount of information
versus if it only has access to Pure
local information
and uh that that's just something to
like
I think for us to note as we look
through models
like are we modeling the generative
process oh so the seasons oscillate so
it is a sine wave
so then the generative model of the
agent is also going to be fitting a side
wave
well then
it kind of collapses to like a
stochastic regression
and maybe then it looks like the fit is
going to be very good
active inference modeling brings in
another complexity with action
influencing outcomes
that prevents some
um I guess fallacies of modeling but by
no means all it probably introduces many
others Eric
yeah uh can you hear me uh this is a
news sounds good um so this this might
be a time to to um to discuss the
question I posted and I apologize I
didn't put it in the right place the
other day
um I just figured out today that it goes
under this particular location but this
is about the question about
um
why modeling of a generative process is
necessary
is a necessary step for building an
active inference model so let me just
read it
um yeah because it's a lot of words uh
so you know we know that an active
inference agent employs a generative
model as this model of the external
world and it uses its General model to
perform inferences about perceptual
input and to make decisions about actors
so in general the external world is
complex and unknowable to the uh to the
agent the generative model may or may
not be able to learn but if learning is
supposed to uh if it is learning is
opposed to put the generative model in a
better alignment with the world's
generative process whatever that may be
so I can see how one might model the
generative process
if one is building an artificial agent
in a laboratory where you kind of have
access you you control how the world
behaves with respect to the agent and
then you might want to study how well
the agent design
um Works versus you know one versus
another under control conditions but
this is not the same as designing an
agent to go out and cope with some real
world environment where you really don't
know what the generative process is so I
think that the recipe for designing an
active interest models would
include formally setting up the
generative process only in the kind of a
laboratory situation but not if you're
really trying to build something out you
know for the for the real world because
you don't
know the general process you might
create an artificial laboratory kind of
situation by trying to build a model of
how the world works and say well how
does my agent work under that those
assumptions or not but that you know
that might set you up for putting the
agent in the real world but in in fact
you don't know the degenerative process
if you're really trying to build
something to to work in the real real
world
That's my kind of my question that's a
question
thank you Lyle
well I I love uh Eric I love that that
framing because I think there's multiple
different cases right so I think if
you're modeling something uh that as you
say goes in in the real world then you
know perhaps it's a you know some
sentient creature or being
um then
then it could obviously there's
the real world even if we knew
everything about it is too complex to
model right so so that's that's Fool's
Gold you know to assume you know
everything right
there and and so I don't I'm just gonna
say yeah that's hard you know typically
I guess we would say what are the parts
of the generative the real world
degenerative uh process that we're going
to
consider relevant and deal with that and
knowing that we're making a leap of
faith but there's another case I think
which is is more generalizable just to
come a complex adaptive systems that
operate in what I call the built world
all right so uh I'm I work with a bunch
of people who build digital twins they
build digital twins of
um human infrastructure
right so buildings and all this stuff
they're the generative process that
we're concerned with is largely knowable
right and largely represent
representable and so and and what's
interesting about that is there are a
bunch of blind spots and inadequacies in
what we know about that generative
process and the ability to do inference
about what the real state of that system
is then becomes the value of this
approach in that setting right so so I
think I I don't think there's a general
answer once again I think it really
comes down to purpose and what the
specific framing you're looking to do to
me this ability to say something about
what I I like that idea of decision
agents right decision agents that uh are
going to potentially take action or
infer actual States
is is much richer than what a lot of the
modeling historical modeling paradigms
have given us so I think that's really
interesting
thank you Lyle Ali
uh yeah and uh I also think that the
distinction between uh General surprises
and generative models
becomes significant uh if we want to
simulate learning rather than just
inference uh I mean that's the answer I
got from Ryan Smith because I asked him
almost the same question why would why
do we need generative process in order
to
simulate the agents and
um because you see for the generative
process
uh
if if the generative model exactly Maps
them to generative process we only need
that capital D Matrix right but uh and
that just when we're just trying to
stimulate the inference side of the
agent right but when the learning comes
along then we need to separate uh that
capital d uh from another Matrix
probably
the case D which Maps into the generator
process so yeah one of the situations
that the distinction between two might
be necessary is when we when those two
process I mean learning and inference
are taken as two separate phenomena to
model
thanks
um one note is also there's work on
symmetries in the generative process
generative model like I think like the
bi-directional paper with Matt Sims and
blue
um discussing it and then
um
here will be a defense to Eric's
excellent question
um
The Entity first modeling approach
that's taken by this chapter
one can say I don't know whether I'm
going to a forest or a desert but I'm
going to have these sensors on my
designed interface
and I'm going to do extensive modeling
on interception and homeostasis
and if I can learn policies that balance
homeostasis
then I've survived
if I fail then
failure happens
so that doesn't mean that it works or
it's doing the right thing fit for
purpose any of those aspects but one of
the insights from the 4E and the
embodied side is like a vast amount of
our
what is modelable as cognitive
isn't necessarily
the declarative
I think therefore I am
possibly even symbolic type thinking
linguistic
there's a lot going on
and many of that a lot going on
can be simplified by not even knowing
about the external process maybe not
even the as modeled kidney knowing about
what the as modeled liver is doing
so this type of a focus was like we're
going to Define
our entity types
and the kinds of observations that they
can make the kinds of affordances that
they have or do empirically or that they
conceptually could do
that approach
um is consistent with embodied
biological systems and Persistence of
organizations and
so I'm wondering how that piece comes
into play with this discussion that's
very important about and also their
their
earlier discussion of the embedded and
extended cognition is that it kind of
blurs the line
with what is a generative model what is
a generative process
so
hence there being a lot of
thinking and attention
on what the system's modeling is
what are the known unknowns and the
unknown unknown is going to be
let's just see
um
a chapter ends
six seven simulating visualizing
analyzing and fitting data using active
inference
so
standard routines for active inference
that provide support for all functions
are available
#spm
and appendix C
step-by-step model is a great
look through this this is Matlab code
one amazing work that we could all
iterate on would be porting Matlab
into the ontology
into Python and or Julia with pi mdp or
active block friends
but there's a lot in SPM and some of its
neuroimaging specific some of it's very
variational base specific not all of it
is going to be state-of-the-art
or the most useful in every situation
however
I wonder if only offering certain
routines in Matlab
which is like a traditionally very
academic
software platform and potentially
non-free
um
can be a limiting factor so
those who feel like they want to learn
more or contribute this way
helping
structure some of the code
architecture so it cohorts coming
through
can be doing multiple language maybe
first we can just move some of these
routines into a folder
and then people can start to organize
those types of um aspects
summary
it's a four-step recipe
we walk through it from the
consideration of the system of Interest
broadly like the entity and the process
focusing in on the entity specifically
thinking structurally about what it is
going to be like doing slash composed of
specifying that to a few levels of
detail then doing the same for the
generative process and then once that is
specified
it's not quite quite there
for most people today but
where
it seems like they are laying out a path
towards and where we probably can and
will be after that level of setup
in some potentially graphical editor or
parameter file
then
as as SPM and Matlab have done in many
many papers the generative model
specification almost prepares the
working script
but there's still a lot of details and
and pieces to add in especially in a
modern environment and for all of these
like non-standard and novel cases that
people are wanting to consider but that
is once we have a notebook that goes
through the recipe
then the recipes can be forked and so on
and they can be written in different
languages Pi mdp block friends Ali
yeah and just one thing that I think is
not made made explicit in this chapter
is that actually that first step which
system are we modeling especially uh the
identification of the marker blanket
part is uh basically at this point of
active inference research uh is more
like a like a hypothetical step because
um
I I also had a misapprehension that uh
we can somehow uh identify the markup
blankets from data but then as I went on
through my project and by Consulting
Maxwell and others
um actually this is the comment Maxwell
uh made about my proposal that he said
that identifying markup blanket from
data is still an outstanding issue that
is not resolved yet in the uh research
and active inference and one of the most
active areas areas of research they're
doing at versus lab is just focused on
this part of the modeling recipe I mean
how to how we can
identify automatically identify or
somehow learn the markup blanket from
just pure data points
awesome and that ties in with Dalton s's
work on the blanket index and like
continuous variables for dynamic
Assemblies of blanketing like it this is
gonna get really
nuanced and empirical
with the discovery and the thresholding
of Markov blankets and causal inference
in Real World Systems with many
different kinds of sensors and doing
structure learning on generative model
and process and like everything
empirically which is why as a
simplifying step
[Music]
um
the uh it actually really reminds me of
how Dave Snowden
situates the difference between systems
thinking and complexity thinking
which is systems often uses like a lot
of nodes and flow charts to represent
system elements and relationships and
like interfaces whereas in complexity in
the canevan especially
um framing
it's like more like
self-organizing sand dunes
and so causal relationships might be
very much in flux and it puts a higher
focus on action rather than system
description
especially in situations like moving
your head where the relationship of
different things
is going to be heavily action dependent
um and so for now we're kind of in the
systems world where it's like a priori
hero the system interfaces
and then we're going to take whether
it's a heuristic or whether you take a
literal interpretation but you don't
have to
you could just say I'm taking
heuristically
the approach of the systems mapping
but that's not to say that that
generative model couldn't be trained in
a systems mapped
context
and then placed into a different setting
where there was a mismatch or a
different generative model
and so it's going to be an ongoing
discussion how are when are these lines
drawn one other point
um other than not needing to use last
names to refer to specific Concepts
um like
are we talking about the blanket that's
statistically insulates every
partition of nodes in these base graphs
which are going to be vast
as Ali and Jacob and I were discussing
on the um branching time active
inference from uh just a few days ago
yesterday
like these graphs are going to be vast
and so just saying there will be a
markout blanket in fact there will be
many Markov blankets with different
semantics that you might assign to them
or not
how does that map onto the real world is
like
the realism instrumentalism
pragmatism abduction conversation that
we've been having do you come in with
these kinds of boundaries
heuristically and distinctions
or how many levels
of uncertainty in nesting I don't know
how many categories of blank there are
I don't know if it's a category or a
Continuum of this
you can actually still take on multiple
levels of uncertainty in the modeling
but then fitting it with empirical data
if it's fit for purpose use is to do
some sort of statistical inference or
like provide meaning or action
but just didactically when the model's
purpose is educational then there's a
lot of things in architectures we might
play with
and then the recipe and also this
conversation uh
helps I hope hold space for the
educational and the Curiosity driven
model development where we're going to
have a lot of fun and interesting
GMS
and
people's applications
and working with different real world
constraints
in different settings we'll all be
learning a lot
from it
and hopefully some of it will be
in repos we can reference
other people may want to play around
inversion within Boulders that we can
make
if anybody wants to be added as a
collaborator in this
textbook repo which is just pretty much
empty
except for I guess a script from Jacob
and there'll be more to say on probably
GitHub and on
um as we continue through but in these
last minutes does anyone have any
thoughts for our continuation of the
cohort
I have one one question uh Daniel you
referenced a paper earlier in the
discussion
um
that I'd love to get the reference to
about uh Persistence of organizations
and survivability
oh yes
um all right
I will put it into
um
into resources
here here's the work
um
it's a PhD dissertation that was
published as a book and I'll upload the
PDF as well this is uh extremely
interesting
work
and okay yeah just it just came out and
um
uh
okay
in our last minutes it's too too fun not
to share
foreign
has written the forward
um
what is a firm's purpose what is an
organization's purpose
it's as difficult to answer as why am I
here free energy governance
and the fep
inverts the question
instead of asking how a system how must
the system behave to survive it asks how
do systems that survive behave
the answer is rather deflationary they
survive their purpose is just
sustainability
so
some classic fristianisms
um some very nice framings on page 95
there's uh
some great juxtapositions
so it it's always awesome to see this
kind of quality
work
and
who knows what people here will see and
I don't see any scripts here
that's the textbook but
who knows
maybe we can do some generative modeling
of organizations or we can
specify it and iterate on it
realize it in Block friends and pi mdp
and Forney lab and jf's symbolic sweet
so there'll be a lot of fun things to
explore this cohort
any other questions or ideas that people
want to share
thanks and congratulations to people for
joining this continuation it's a a great
continuance
and
well I know that this part is going to
be very interesting
the next three months will be
interesting